Hi, my name is Junyue.
Hi, 我是俊跃
I'm a software engineer who works for
我是多媒体团队的软件工程师
multi-media team at Bytedance.
来自字节跳动
Today I will talk about our web based non-linear
今天我想分享一下我们的
video editor written in C++ and built with
基于 Web 的非线性视频编辑器
WebAssembly and EMScripten. slide-2
它是用 C++ 编写，并且用 WebAssembly 和 EMScripten 进行搭建 slide-2
Slide 2
Slide 2
This is the agenda of my talk.
这是我的演讲的几个主题
First I will introduce what the video editor is.
首先我会介绍一下这个视频编辑器是做什么的
Secondly I will briefly introduce how it works.
然后我会简单介绍其工作原理
And lastly I will talk about some needs
最后我会讲讲
for our development. slide-3
开发过程中的一些开发者需求 slide-3
Slide 3
Slide 3
Video editing is very important for every
视频剪辑对每一位视频内容创作者而言
video content creator.
都是非常重要的
It is one of the last steps of video creation.
它是视频创作的最终步骤之一
It turns your media clips into a complete story.
它能把你的视频片段变成一个完整的故事
There are many video editing software including
现有有很多的视频剪辑软件
desktop applications, mobile applications
包括桌面应用和移动应用
or maybe some cloud based software. 24-p
或者基于云的软件 24-p
What we are buiding is a web based multi-track video editor.
我们所做的则是一款基于 Web 构建的多轨视频剪辑器
Users can use a web browser to add video clips,
用户可以通过 Web 浏览器添加视频剪辑
audio clips, subtitles, transitions and special effects.
音频片段，字幕，过渡，特效等等
By taking advantage of web technology and
利用 Web 技术
cloud based storage, users can open the projects
和云存储，用户可以
with any computer at any time and continue to work. slide-4
在任何时间任何电脑上打开项目继续工作 slide-4
Slide 4
Slide 4
At first our core engine code was written
一开始我们的核心引擎
for native platforms in C++.
是使用 C++ 写在 native 原生平台的
It is a multi-threaded engine which runs
它是个多线程的引擎
on Android, iOS, Windows and MacOS.
可以在 Android, iOS, Windows 以及 MacOS 上运行
With the improvement of the browser's support
随着浏览器
for WebAssembly, we now have the opportunity
对 WebAssembly 的支持和优化，我们现在有机会
to migrate the engine to the web. 40-p
把这个引擎迁移到 Web 40-p
We use WebGL and other technologies for
我们使用了 WebGL 和其它的一些相关技术
real-time video rendering.
进行实时视频渲染
In fact, WebAssembly is not a very new technology anymore,
其实，WebAssembly 已经不再是个新技术
so I won't talk about every detail of
所以这里不再详细阐述
WebAssembly and EMScripten here. slide-5
WebAssembly 和 EMScripten 的每一个技术细节 slide-5
Slide 5
Slide 5
This diagram shows a simplest structure of the application.
这个图表展示了这款应用的一个简单架构
We provide JS APIs to the web page to control the engine.
我们为网页提供 JS APIs 从而操控这个引擎
The JS APIs call to C++ engine compiled with EMScripten.
这些 JS APIs 唤起 C++ 引擎使用 EMScripten 进行编译
And the C++ engine calls the browser feature APIs
同时 C++ 引擎唤起 EMScripten 提供的浏览器特色 API
provided by EMScripten to use all the features.
去执行相关功能
Such as WebGL for video and special effect rendering,
例如视频和特效渲染的 WebGL 相关操作
WebAudio for audio playback, Web Workers for multi-threaded
用 WebAudio 实现音频播放，Web Workers 实现多线程运行时
runtime and IndexedDB for file system persistence. slide-6
以及用 IndexedDB 进行文件系统持久式存储 slide-6
Slide 6
Slide 6
This is a diagram to illustrate the simplest process to
这个图表展示了在一个简单的视频处理流程中
show what browser features are used in the processing route. 60-p
有哪些浏览器功能被用到处理途径中 60-p
First, the video part.
首先，视频部分
For each video track, we first use WebAssembly
对每个视频轨迹，我们首先都使用到了 WebAssembly
to decode the video frame.
进行视频帧的解码
After we get the decoded video, we convert it into texture,
获得已解码的视频后，我们把它转换成纹理 texture
and then blend the textures of multiple video tracks
然后把多个视频轨迹的纹理进行混合
and display it on canvas through WebGL. 67-p
并且通过 WebGL 把它们显示到 canvas 67-p
For the audio part, we also use WebAssembly to decode,
在音频部分，我们也使用了 WebAssembly 进行解码
and then send the decoded data to WebAudio API for playback. 70-p
然后把解码后的数据发送到 Web Audio API 进行播放 70-p
Of course, for any kind of video player,
当然，对所有的视频播放器
audio and video synchronization is indispensable.
音视频同步是必不可少的
Here is just the simplest processing route.
这里展示的是一个简化后的处理途径
I have omitted many steps.
我省略了很多步骤
The actual situation is much more complex than
实际的解决方案
that shown in the figure. slide-7
会比这里展示的复杂得多 slide-7
Slide 7
Slide 7
So far, we've basically made the whole application work,
到此，我们基本可以让这个应用跑起来
but that doesn't mean it's perfect.
但这并不意味着它已经是完美的
There are unsatisfactory things at some points. 82-p
在某些地方还是很不尽人意 82-p
The first problem is decoding performance.
第一个问题是解码操作的性能
We need to decode multiple video tracks at the same time,
我们需要同时对多个视频轨道进行解码
which is a great challenge for the performance
对性能而言
of video decoding.
是音频解码方面很大的挑战
Using WebAssembly to decode will consume a lot of CPU,
使用 WebAssembly 进行解码会耗费大量的 CPU 资源
and its speed is not as fast as native.
而且它的速度比不上 native
At present, in order to support as many video tracks as
到现在为止，为了支持尽可能多的视频轨道
possible, we limit the video resolution to 480p. 91-p
我们把视频的分辨率限制在 480p 91-p
With the introduction of WebCodecs, we may have the
通过引入 WebCodecs
opportunity to improve our video resolution.
我们也许有机会改善我们的视频分辨率
To use WebCodecs in a thread, that is a worker, providing
在一个线程中使用 WebCodecs, 即一个 worker
synchronized WebCodecs API will be more friendly
使用同步的 WebCodecs API
for C++ code to integrate. slide-8
对 C++ 代码来说集成起来更加友好 slide-8
Slide 8
Slide 8
Another one is better debugging experience. 100-p
另一个需求是更好的调试体验 100-p
When enabling the debug mode of DWARF,
在允许 DWARF 的 debug 模式时
the WASM file will become very large.
WASM 文件体积会变得特别庞大
In our case, it is more than 1 GB,
对我们而言，它超过了 1 GB
which causes the browser to be very unstable.
这会让浏览器变成非常不稳定
The browser will crash easily after running for a while.
运行一段时间后浏览器会非常容易崩溃
And it's slow.
而且速度缓慢
Even when debugging in localhost, loading the DWARF
哪怕是在 localhost 进行调试
information will still take more than 10 seconds.
加载 DWARF 也需要花费超过10秒的时间
And the devtools often respond slowly and get stuck. 110-p
而且这个开发者工具反应缓慢并且很容易卡住 110-p
Secondly, in a multi-threaded application,
其次，在一个多线程应用中
a meaningful thread name, that is the name of the worker,
一个有含义的线程命名，也就是 worker 的名字
is very useful for debugging.
对调试来说是非常有帮助的
The current Web Worker only supports
现在的 Web Worker 只支持
specifying its name when it is created.
在它被创建时候指定的名字
We hope it can be renamed when using a Web Worker,
我们希望能在 Web Worker 使用过程中运行对它进行重命名
which is very helpful to find the desired thread. 118-p
这会对定位所需要找到的线程非常有帮助 118-p
Thirdly, we need to stop the world.
第三，我们需要允许一个中止全部的操作
At present, devtools can only select a thread
当前，开发者工具只能选择一个线程
and click the pause button.
并点击暂停按钮
It will pause the worker or main thread.
它会暂停这个 worker 或者主线程
But when there are a lot of threads,
但当同时存在很多的线程的时候
I have to click the pause button one by one.
就需要一个接一个地点击暂停按钮
Similarly, the resume button now
类似的，现在的重启按钮
needs to be clicked one by one.
也需要一个接一个地点击
In this regard, I think we can refer to
在这方面，我认为我们可以参照
the debugging habits of the popular IDEs. slide-9
大部分流行的 IDE 的调试习惯 slide-9
Slide 9
Slide 9
As shown in the figure, EMScripten provides a file system
如这张图显示的，EMScripten 提供了一个文件系统
that supports the direct use of native POSIX file APIs.
支持直接使用原生的 POSIX 文件 API
On the browser, it mainly includes MEMFS and IDBFS. 134-p
对浏览器而言，它主要引入了 MEMFS 和 IDBFS. 134-p
However, video files are often large.
然而，视频文件通常体积庞大
When we use MEMFS to read large files,
当我们使用 MEMFS 去读大文件时
the memory consumption will be large because it loads
内存的消耗会非常大
the whole file into memory, which is very easy
因为它把整个文件读进了内存
to cause out-of-memory errors.
这会非常容易导致 out-of-memory error
At the same time, multi-threaded access
同时，多线程访问
will always proxy to the main thread,
总是会在主线程创建代理
which has an impact on the performance of the main thread. 143-p
导致对主线程一定程度的性能影响 143-p
Therefore, I think we need a file system
因此，我认为我们需要一个更好的文件系统
that supports better multi-threaded accessing,
支持更完备的多线程访问
less memory consuming and better persistence solutions. 147-p
和更少的内存消耗以及更好的持久化方案 147-p
OK. That's all for me.
OK。这是我今天希望跟大家分享的内容
Thank you very much.
非常感谢